Emhart Corporation Records
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Emhart Corporation Records.
undated, 1883-1989
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Emhart Corporation.
23 linear feet.
MSS19890085
Emhart Corporation was a multinational company located in Farmington, Connecticut. Prior to its 1989 merger with Black & Decker, Emhart operated in over one hundred countries with a world-wide work force of 30,000 employees. Emhart's products included machines for the manufacture of glass bottles and shoes; filling, sealing and packaging machinery; security systems; electronics; chemical products; metal fasteners; rubber processing equipment; and consumer and do-it-yourself products. Brand name products included True Temper® hardware and sporting goods, and Price Pfister® plumbing fixtures. Emhart's domestic roots went back to the American Hardware Company, founded in New Britain, Connecticut, in 1902.
History
Emhart Corporation was a multinational company located in Farmington, Connecticut. Prior to its 1989 merger with Black & Decker, Emhart operated in over one hundred countries with a worldwide work force of 30,000 employees. Emhart's products included machines for the manufacture of glass bottles and shoes; filling, sealing and packaging machinery; security systems; electronics; chemical products; metal fasteners; rubber processing equipment; and consumer and do-it-yourself products. Brand name products included True Temper® hardware and sporting goods, and Price Pfister® plumbing fixtures.
Emhart's domestic roots went back to the American Hardware Company, founded in New Britain, Connecticut, in 1902. Ten years later, the company merged with the Hartford-Empire Company, a glass factory, and the name Emhart Manufacturing Company came into being. Over the next several decades, a series of mergers followed, both domestic and foreign, until Emhart Manufacturing emerged as the world's leading glass-machinery maker. In 1976, the company merged with the United Shoe Machinery Company, founded in Boston, Massachusetts in 1899. United Shoe had followed a similar path of growth and acquisition both at home and abroad, and the merger of these two giants produced the modern-day Emhart Corporation.
In 1989, in order to resist a $2.4 billion takeover attempt by a New York investment group (which included oil heir, Gordon P. Getty), Emhart merged with Black & Decker Corporation. The merged company operates from Black & Decker's headquarters in Towson, Maryland. The company headquarters in Farmington, Connecticut, were closed in June 1989.
Scope and Content
The collection contains corporate and subsidiary administrative materials from 1883-1989 [1951-1989]. Included are correspondence, memoranda, reports, stock agreements, price books, product manuals, product specifications, news briefs and releases, newspaper clippings, and videotapes. Organizations mentioned in the collection include: divisions of Emhart, Airway Products, Akticbolaget Sundvalls Verlestader, American Hardware Corporation, Arcotronics, Barber-Colman Akticbolag, Bob Goshe Company, Bostik, Broad View Chemical, B.U. Supplies and Machinery Company, Ltd., Casady Engineering Associates, Connecticut Kellering, Inc., Consumers Cordage Company, Inc., Corbin Cabinet Lock Company, Corbin Clamp, Corbin Motor Vehicle Corporation, P & F Corbin, Corbin Screw Corporation, Cordo-Hyde Company, Inc., Crown-Metro, David Bridge and Company, Ltd., Dynapert, Dynapert-H & C Corporation, Emhart Canada Ltd., Emhart Scandia AB, Empire Machine Company, Finch Paint and Chemical Company, Garden America, Green Sales, Inc., H & O Strong and Sons, Ltd., HTC Corporation, Hartford-Empire Company, Hartford-Fairmont Company, Hartlung Fasteners, Henry and Wright, C. V. Hill and Company, C. V. Hill of Canada, Hill Corporation, Hill Refrigerators of Canace, Hoague-Sprague, Household Aids, Inc., Icon, Industrial Instruments, Inpak, Inter-Coastal Shoe Machinery, International Hardware of Canada, Irish Shoe Supplies, Ltd., Kwikset, LaClade-Christy, Lombard Industries, Maquinas Imical, Moira Investments Ltd., Monitor Industries, Mullen Brothers, National Shoe Foundation for Disabled Feet, Inc., undated Industries, Inc., Never-Seez Compound Corporation, Nippon Pop Rivets, O. A. Miller (Ireland) Ltd, O.A. Miller Lasting Company, Ltd., USM Orthopedic Research Lab, Parker Kalon, PCI Group, Inc.; Pearson & Bennion Ltd., Pickering Gov. Company, Plastic Machinery Company, Inc., Plax Corporation, Plymouth Cordage Industries, Inc., Powers Manufacturing, Inc., Price Pfister, P. R. Mallory and Company, Redington, Inc., Royton Realty, Russel and Erwin Manufacturing Company, Safe Hardware, Samco-Strong, Ltd., Savage Arms Corporation, Schaffer Magnetics, Shoe Farm, Inc., Sistemas de Fajacion Tucker, Skyworker, Spiras Systems, Standard Knapp, Standard Tool Company, Technical Devices Company, Texon, Inc., Thomas Haley and Company, Ltd., Transamerican Shoe Machinery, True Temper, Truelove and McClean, Tucker Products, Inc., Turner Machinery, Ltd., Turner Tanning Machinery, United Awl and Needle Company, U.S. Gear Corporation, United Marketing, Ltd., USMC International, Ltd., United Shoe Machinery Corporation, U & O Press, Vibrac Corporation, Warren Fastener, William De Boule Company, and Woodmont Products.
Arrangement
Series I: Administrative Files ( undated, 1942-1989 ) contain the company's mission statement, annual reports, letters to stockholders, stock agreements, Securities and Exchange Commission correspondence, price books and product manuals, product specifications, news briefs and releases, newspaper clippings and video tapes. The materials are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Series II: Subsidiaries, Affiliates and Acquisitions ( undated, 1883-1989 ) consist of memoranda, reports and correspondence with companies doing business with or part of Emhart's multinational holdings. The series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
Series III: Shareholders Files ( 1908-1987 ) contains annual reports, letters to stockholders and notices of meetings of six subsidiary companies of Emhart Corporation: American Hardware Corporation, Hartford-Empire Company, Hill Corporation, Plax Corporation, Savage Arms Corporation and United Shoe Machinery Corporation. The materials are arranged alphabetically by name of subsidiary.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Connecticut business and industry. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Hartford-Empire Company.; Emhart Manufacturing Company.; United Shoe Machinery Corporation.; American Hardware Company.; Manufactures—Connecticut.; Machinery industry—Connecticut.; Shoe machinery industry.; Glass manufacture.; Machinery in industry.; Connecticut—Business, industries, and trades—Manufactures.; Connecticut—Business, industries, and trades—Shoes.; Connecticut—Business, industries, and trades—Glass.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Publications.; Photographs.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; Videocassettes.; Audio cassettes.
Occupations:
Manufacturer.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The Emhart Corporation Records were donated to the Historical Manuscripts and Archives Department (now Archives & Special Collections) by the Emhart Corporation in two separate accessions in May and August of 1989.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Administrative Files, undated, 1942-1989
  - Mission statement, 1977-1986 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Reports, 1960-1980 (Box 1:, Folder 2-5)
  - Annual Reports, 1951-1988 (Box 1:, Folder 6-16)
  - Notices of Annual Meetings, 1969-1975 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - Quarterly reports, 1964-1988 (Box 2:, Folder 18-20)
  - Prospectuses, 1964-1988 (Box 2:, Folder 21-24)
  - Letters to Stockholders, 1952-1976 (Box 2:, Folder 25)
  - Notices of annual meetings, 1953-1975 (Box 2:, Folder 26)
  - Proxy statements, 1964-1972 (Box 2:, Folder 27)
  - Presidents' remarks, 1958-1985 (Box 2:, Folder 28)
  - “Dialogues with Current and Former Retail Shareholders”, 1978 (Box 2:, Folder 29-30)
  - Stock transmittal forms, 1953 (Box 2:, Folder 31)
  - Stock order forms, 1975 (Box 2:, Folder 32)
  - Stock agreements, 1985-1987 (Box 2:, Folder 33)
  - Stock issue reports, 1985-1987 (Box 2:, Folder 34-35)
  - Securities and Exchange Commission, 1986-1988 (Box 2:, Folder 36-42)
  - Graphics Identification Standards Manual, 1988 (Box 3:, Folder 43)
  - Sourcebook, 1988 (Box 3:, Folder 44-45)
  - Price books, 1988; (4 vols.)
  - Price books, 1988; (6 vols.) (Box 4)
  - Product manuals, 1956-1982; (6 vols.) (Box 5:, Folder 46-47)
  - Product manuals, 1981-1982; (8 vols.) (Box 6)
  - Product specifications, 1951-1975 (Box 7-13)
  - Product specifications, undated; (2 vols.) (Box 14)
  - Air Transportation Section, 1955 (Box 14:, Folder 48)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1962-1963 (Box 14:, Folder 49)
  - Scrapbooks, 1942-1964
  - Emhart News, 1972-1989 (Box 15)
  - Seven inch reel tapes, 1969; (4 reels) (Box 16)
  - Audio Cassette tapes, 1963-1987; (16)
  - Video tapes, 1979-1988; (11)
  - Articles by T. Mitchell Ford, 1975-1985 (Box 17:, Folder 50)
  - Photographs, 1950-1979; (5 albums) (Box 17:, Folder 51-52)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1968-1977 (Box 18, Folder 53-56)
  - News briefs and releases, 1966-1982 (Box 18:, Folder 57-63)
- Series II: Subsidiaries, Affiliates and Acquisitions, undated, 1883-1989
  - Acquisitions and divestitures, 1988 (Box 19:, Folder 64)
  - Advanced Technologies, 1989 (Box 19:, Folder 65)
  - Airway Products, 1984 (Box 19:, Folder 66)
  - Akticbolaget Sundvalls Verlestader, 1978 (Box 19:, Folder 67)
  - American Hardware Corporation, 1953-1981 (Box 19:, Folder 68-69)
  - Ammo, 1988 (Box 19:, Folder 70)
  - Arcotronics, 1985 (Box 19:, Folder 71)
  - A.T. chronological files, 1981-1984 (Box 19:, Folder 72-74)
  - Bailey, 1985 (Box 19:, Folder 75)
  - Barber-Colman Akticbolag, 1984 (Box 19:, Folder 76)
  - Bob Goshe Company, undated (Box 19:, Folder 77)
  - Bostik, 1985 (Box 19:, Folder 78)
  - Bostick-Finch, 1985 (Box 19:, Folder 79)
  - Bostik, Japan, 1984 (Box 19:, Folder 80)
  - Bostik, West, 1985 (Box 19:, Folder 81)
  - Broad View Chemical, 1982 (Box 19:, Folder 82)
  - B.U. Supplies and Machinery Company, Ltd., undated (Box 19:, Folder 83)
  - C-Day divestiture, 1984 (Box 19:, Folder 84)
  - Casady Engineering Associates, 1973-1984 (Box 19:, Folder 85)
  - Connecticut Kellering, Inc., undated (Box 19:, Folder 86)
  - Consumers Cordage Company, Inc., 1971 (Box 19:, Folder 87)
  - Converter, 1985 (Box 19:, Folder 88)
  - Corbin Cabinet Lock Company, 1946-1981 (Box 19:, Folder 89)
  - “Early Locks and Lockmakers of America”, 1976 (Box 19:, Folder 90)
  - Corbin Clamp, 1925, 1981-87 (Box 19:, Folder 91)
  - Corbin Motor Vehicle Corporation, 1957-1961 (Box 19:, Folder 92)
  - P & F Corbin, 1904 (Box 19:, Folder 93)
  - Corbin Screw Corporation, 1957 (Box 19:, Folder 94)
  - Cordo-Hyde Company, Inc., 1974 (Box 19:, Folder 95)
  - Crown-Metro, 1974 (Box 19:, Folder 96)
  - David Bridge and Company, Ltd., undated (Box 19:, Folder 97)
  - Dynapert, 1984 (Box 19:, Folder 98)
  - Dynapert-H & C Corporation, 1985 (Box 19:, Folder 99)
  - Emhart Canada Ltd., 1986 (Box 19:, Folder 100)
  - Emhart Corporation, 1976-1987 (Box 19:, Folder 101)
  - Emhart Profile, 1955-1989 (Box 19:, Folder 102)
  - “Recollections of P.R. Mallory”, 1966 (Box 19:, Folder 103)
  - Emhart trademark file, 1920-1971 (Box 19:, Folder 104)
  - Emhart Company tree, 1974 (Box 19:, Folder 105)
  - Emhart Industries, 1987 (Box 19:, Folder 106)
  - Emhart Manufacturing Company, 1964 (Box 19:, Folder 107)
  - Emhart Scandia AB, 1984 (Box 19:, Folder 108)
  - Empire Machine Company, undated (Box 19:, Folder 109)
  - Esser, 1984 (Box 19:, Folder 110)
  - Farrel, 1979-1987 (Box 19:, Folder 111)
  - Farrel Bridge, 1987 (Box 19:, Folder 112)
  - Fastener, 1969-1984 (Box 19:, Folder 113)
  - Fellows, 1986-1987 (Box 19:, Folder 114)
  - Finch Paint and Chemical Company, 1984 (Box 19:, Folder 115)
  - French operations, undated (Box 19:, Folder 116)
  - Garden America, 1989 (Box 19:, Folder 117)
  - George Tucker Eyelet, undated (Box 19:, Folder 118)
  - Girder, undated (Box 19:, Folder 119)
  - Green Sales, Inc., undated (Box 19:, Folder 120)
  - Hardware Division, Emhart Corporation, undated (Box 20:, Folder 121)
  - Harmonic Drive, 1979-1988 (Box 20:, Folder 122)
  - H & O Strong and Sons, Ltd., undated (Box 20:, Folder 123)
  - HTC Corporation, 1985 (Box 20:, Folder 124)
  - Hartford Division, Emhart, 1973 (Box 20:, Folder 125)
  - Hartford-Empire Company, 1940 (Box 20:, Folder 126)
  - Hartford-Fairmont Company, 1912-1928 (Box 20:, Folder 127)
  - Hartlung Fasteners, undated (Box 20:, Folder 128)
  - Henry and Wright, 1942-1982 (Box 20:, Folder 129)
  - Hill Agreement, 1986 (Box 20:, Folder 130)
  - C. V. Hill and Company, undated (Box 20:, Folder 131)
  - C. V. Hill of Canada, undated (Box 20:, Folder 132)
  - Hill Refrigerators of Canada, 1971 (Box 20:, Folder 133)
  - Hoague-Sprague, 1985 (Box 20:, Folder 134)
  - Household Aids, Inc., undated (Box 20:, Folder 135)
  - Icon, undated (Box 20:, Folder 136)
  - Industrial Instruments, undated (Box 20:, Folder 137)
  - Inpak, undated (Box 20:, Folder 138)
  - Inter-Coastal Shoe Machinery, 1982 (Box 20:, Folder 139)
  - International Hardware of Canada, undated (Box 20:, Folder 140)
  - Irish Shoe Supplies, Ltd., 1985 (Box 20:, Folder 141)
  - Kwikset, 1985 (Box 20:, Folder 142)
  - LaClade-Christy, 1973-1987 (Box 20:, Folder 143-145)
  - Lombard Industries, 1977-1985 (Box 20:, Folder 146)
  - Machinery Division Beverly, 1987 (Box 20:, Folder 147)
  - Mallory, 1988 (Box 20:, Folder 148)
  - Maquinas Imical, 1983 (Box 20:, Folder 149)
  - Maxim Silencer, 1955 (Box 20:, Folder 150)
  - Mite, 1985 (Box 20:, Folder 151)
  - Moira Investments Ltd., undated (Box 20:, Folder 152)
  - Molly Division-Bostik, 1982 (Box 20:, Folder 153)
  - Monitor Industries, undated (Box 20:, Folder 154)
  - Mullen Brothers, undated (Box 20:, Folder 155)
  - National Shoe Foundation for Disabled Feet, Inc., 1950 (Box 20:, Folder 156)
  - undated Industries, Inc., 1984 (Box 20:, Folder 157)
  - Never-Seez Compound Corporation, 1982 (Box 20:, Folder 158)
  - Nippon Pop Rivets, undated (Box 20:, Folder 159)
  - Notifier, 1983-1988 (Box 20:, Folder 160)
  - Nylok, 1984 (Box 20:, Folder 161)
  - O. A. Miller (Ireland) Ltd., 1985 (Box 20:, Folder 162)
  - O.A. Miller Lasting Company, Ltd., 1983 (Box 20:, Folder 163)
  - USM Orthopedic Research Lab, 1950 (Box 20:, Folder 164)
  - Parker Kalon, 1982-1983 (Box 20:, Folder 165)
  - PCI Group, Inc., 1982-1983 (Box 20:, Folder 166)
  - Pearson & Bennion Ltd., undated (Box 20:, Folder 167)
  - Pickering Gov. Company, undated (Box 20:, Folder 168)
  - Plastic Machinery Company, Inc., 1983 (Box 20:, Folder 169)
  - Plax Corporation, 1986 (Box 20:, Folder 170)
  - Plymouth Cordage Industries, Inc., 1986 (Box 20:, Folder 171)
  - Plymouth College of Canada, Ltd., 1971 (Box 20:, Folder 172)
  - Powers Manufacturing, Inc., 1982-1985 (Box 20:, Folder 173)
  - PRC, undated (Box 21:, Folder 174)
  - Price Pfister, 1988 (Box 21:, Folder 175)
  - P. R. Mallory and Company, 1983 (Box 21:, Folder 176)
  - Redington, Inc., 1985 (Box 21:, Folder 177)
  - Red Sherman, 1983 (Box 21:, Folder 178)
  - Rockwell, undated (Box 21:, Folder 179)
  - Roseway, 1976 (Box 21:, Folder 180)
  - Royton Realty, undated (Box 21:, Folder 181)
  - Russel and Erwin Manufacturing Company, undated (Box 21:, Folder 182)
  - Russwin Division, 1988 (Box 21:, Folder 183)
  - Safe Hardware, undated (Box 21:, Folder 184)
  - Samco-Strong, Ltd., undated (Box 21:, Folder 185)
  - Savage Arms, 1980 (Box 21:, Folder 186)
  - Schaffer Magnetics, undated (Box 21:, Folder 187)
  - Shoe Farm, Inc., 1955, 1982 (Box 21:, Folder 188)
  - Sistemas de Fajacion Tucker, 1972 (Box 21:, Folder 189)
  - Skyworker, 1956-1983 (Box 21:, Folder 190)
  - Spiras Systems, 1971 (Box 21:, Folder 191)
  - Standard Knapp, 1982-1986 (Box 21:, Folder 192)
  - Standard Tool Company, 1983 (Box 21:, Folder 193)
  - Technical Devices Company, undated (Box 21:, Folder 194)
  - Texon, Inc., 1985-1987 (Box 21:, Folder 195)
  - Thomas Haley and Company, Ltd., undated (Box 21:, Folder 196)
  - Transamerican Shoe Machinery, 1971-1984 (Box 21:, Folder 197)
  - True Temper, 1985-1989 (Box 21:, Folder 198-199)
  - Truelove and McClean, undated (Box 21:, Folder 200)
  - Tucker Products, Inc., 1984 (Box 21:, Folder 201)
  - Turner Machinery, Ltd., undated (Box 21:, Folder 202)
  - Turner Tanning Machinery, 1984 (Box 21:, Folder 203)
  - United Awl and Needle Company, 1984 (Box 21:, Folder 204)
  - U.S. Gear Corporation, undated (Box 21:, Folder 205)
  - United Marketing, Ltd., undated (Box 21:, Folder 206)
  - U.S. Home Products Division, 1985 (Box 21:, Folder 207)
  - UPCO, 1983 (Box 21:, Folder 208)
  - USMC International, Ltd., 1981 (Box 21:, Folder 209)
  - United Shoe Machinery, 1940-1980 (Box 21:, Folder 210-212)
    - Acquisitions, 1962-1976 (Box 21:, Folder 213)
    - Foreign Operations, 1950-1970 (Box 21:, Folder 214)
    - Lasting machines, 1883-1972 (Box 21:, Folder 215)
    - Pan American against the government of Cuba, 1969 (Box 21:, Folder 216)
    - Scrapbook, undated (Box 21:, Folder 217)
  - V & O Press, undated (Box 21:, Folder 218-219)
  - Vibrac Corporation, undated (Box 21:, Folder 220)
  - Warren Fastener, undated (Box 21:, Folder 221)
  - Whitman, 1977 (Box 21:, Folder 222)
  - William De Boule Company, Inc., undated (Box 21:, Folder 223)
  - Woodmont Products, 1986 (Box 21:, Folder 224)
  - Wright Machinery Division, 1985 (Box 21:, Folder 225)
- Series III: Shareholders Files, undated, 1908-1987
  - American Hardware Corporation
    - Annual reports, 1908-1963 (Box 22:, Folder 226-230)
    - Quarterly reports, 1955-1964 (Box 22:, Folder 231)
    - Letters to stockholders, 1957-1964 (Box 22:, Folder 232)
    - Notices of annual meeting, 1958-1962 (Box 22:, Folder 233)
  - Hartford-Empire Company
    - Annual reports, 1946-1950 (Box 22:, Folder 234)
    - Letters to stockholders, 1949-1951 (Box 22:, Folder 235)
    - Financial statements, 1940-1945 (Box 22:, Folder 236)
  - Hill Corporation
    - Annual reports, 1960-1962 (Box 22:, Folder 237)
    - Reports to stockholders, 1961 (Box 22:, Folder 238)
    - Notices of annual meeting, 1962-1963 (Box 22:, Folder 239)
  - Plax Corporation
    - Annual reports, 1954-1965 (Box 22:, Folder 240-242)
    - Letters to shareholders, 1965-1966 (Box 22:, Folder 243)
    - Transmittal forms, 1966 (Box 22:, Folder 244)
  - Savage Arms Corporation
    - Annual reports, 1953-1962 (Box 22:, Folder 245-246)
    - Quarterly reports, 1962 (Box 22:, Folder 247)
    - Letters to stockholders, 1963 (Box 22:, Folder 248)
  - United Shoe Machinery Corporation
    - Annual reports, 1908-1975 (Box 22:, Folder 249-261)
    - Notices of annual meeting and proxy statements, 1942-1979 (Box 23:, Folder 262-268)
    - Letters to stockholders, 1951-1975 (Box 23:, Folder 269)
    - Quarterly dividends, 1957-1975 (Box 23:, Folder 270)
    - Quarterly reports, 1953-1975 (Box 23:, Folder 271-273)
    - Summary reports and analyses, 1972 (Box 23:, Folder 274)
    - Agreements, 1931-1969 (Box 23:, Folder 275-277)
    - Correspondence, 1964-1987 (Box 23:, Folder 278)
    - USM Today, 1966-1971 (Box 23:, Folder 279)
    - Brochures, undated (Box 23:, Folder 280)
    - Articles, undated (Box 23:, Folder 281)
    - Footwear News, 1963 (Box 23:, Folder 282)